# **Ryan Parman**

Cloud-native engineering leader with a focus on reliability, scalability, and security for the modern web.

Links: GitHub (personal) • GitHub (side project) • LinkedIn • Stack Overflow • Role-targeted résumés

Format: Web • PDF • Word • OpenDocument • Raw Markdown

# Summary

Ryan Parman is a cloud-native engineering leader with over 25 years of experience, who specializes in technical leadership, software development, site reliability engineering, and cybersecurity for the modern web. A seasoned problem-solver who excels at listening, adapting, and driving continuous improvement. Committed to delivering exceptional work, building impactful solutions, and elevating team performance.

# Work Experience

Older roles are truncated for brevity. If interested, details can be found on GitHub.

### McGraw Hill — Remote (since COVID), previously Seattle, WA

### Principal Engineer, Cloud Center of Excellence (January 2024—October 2024)

- Assumed a role influencing the technical direction of the entire organization. Ensured a focus on real-world, actionable feedback and provided strategic direction aligned with practical needs.
- Continued to be involved in the oversight and direction of our AWS stack, security, guardrails, and more.
- Identified opportunities to extend the security measures and guardrails developed for AWS to other cloud platforms.

### Principal Cloud and Platform Engineer (June 2020—January 2024)

- Transitioned from Engineering Manager to a strategic technical leadership role.
- Prolific documentarian. Documentation is worth 50% of your grade.
- Either directly or collaboratively designed and maintained <u>AWS Control Tower</u>, <u>Artifactory</u>, <u>GitHub Enterprise</u>, <u>GitHub Actions</u>, <u>CircleCI</u>, <u>Jenkins</u>, and more.
- Partnered with McGraw Hill Enterprise Architecture and <u>AWS Professional Services</u> to deploy <u>AWS Control Tower</u> and <u>AWS Identity</u> <u>Center</u>. Lowered costs and increased control over account guardrails.
- Managed the program for building and maintaining base AMIs for all of McGraw Hill. Leveraged insights from the <u>Center of Internet</u> <u>Security</u>, security patching, and the specific needs of internal customers to develop a unified build pipeline integrating best practices.
- Using <u>AWS SDKs</u>, conducted comprehensive scans of Route 53 to obtain a mapping of thousands of active websites owned by McGraw Hill. Focused on identifying and remediating misconfigurations, rotating certificates, and more.
- Co-implemented self-hosted runners for GitHub Actions. Focused on the Linux runtime environment.
- Rebuilt our <u>Artifactory</u> cluster with a "cattle, not pets" approach. Ran the project from inception to completion, including the majority of development. Worked across dozens of teams and hundreds of services to complete the project.
- Enabled continuous token and password rotation for our engineering teams by building a *Token Vending Machine*, providing a "pushbutton, receive-token" solution.
- Proactively added support for lower-cost ARM64 CPUs, opening the door for ~\$450k/year in cost savings.

### **Engineering Manager, Site Reliability (October 2018—June 2020)**

- Managed a team of four, while working to level-up the team's technical skills and leadership capabilities. Conducted regular 1:1s, performance reviews, and career development discussions.
- Led the <u>Site Reliability Engineering</u> (SRE) team in addressing macro-oriented problems affecting decentralized, heterogeneous engineering teams across the company. Empowered greater self-service for engineering teams.
- Revamped the Seattle SRE interview process to prioritize a 70/30 focus on software engineering (Dev) and systems operations (Ops). Emphasized leadership qualities, bias for action, and high curiosity.

- Owned and served as the key decision-maker in development of a core platform for company-wide, reliability-focused projects.
- Formed and led a leadership group to establish a process maintaining reusable Terraform modules which could be composed together according to a service's needs.
- Customized the Amazon Linux AMIs to comply with Level-2 <u>CIS</u> Guidelines for both Amazon Linux and <u>Docker</u>. Collaborated closely
  with cybersecurity, operations, and various business units to ensure compliance.
- Developed custom security and operational tooling where off-the-shelf tools wouldn't give us what we needed, to understand the current posture of ±200 AWS accounts.
- Reduced the time to deploy a new service from dozens of weeks to a single meeting by implementing a Monitoring-as-Code
  methodology, and defining broad-use Service Level Objectives (SLOs).

## Staff Software Engineer (October 2016—October 2018)

- Led the development of multiple Tier-1 services within the educational content authoring pipeline, leveraging technologies such as REST, GraphQL, API design, Amazon ECS, Docker, Terraform, ePubs, and security best practices.
- Provided the technical direction of these projects, promoted their adoption across the organization, provided comprehensive documentation, and offered ongoing guidance on adoption.
- Led the development of the authoring component of <a href="McGraw Hill's SmartBook 2.0 product">McGraw Hill's SmartBook 2.0 product</a>, and the internal system which indexes authored content, builds ePubs, and encodes images/video for McGraw Hill's ePub CDN.
- Introduced the adoption of continuous integration (CI), continuous delivery (CD), rapid deployment practices, and Docker containers.
- Introduced a more hands-on monitoring approach, enabling development teams to actively engage in their own operations. Achieved significantly lower *Mean Time to Recovery* (MTTR).
- Served as a core resource in adopting Infrastructure-as-Code (IaC) tools such as Terraform and Packer.

### WePay — Redwood City, CA

### **DevOps Engineer (April 2015—September 2016)**

- Led a cross-company initiative to upgrade the monolithic application from PHP 5.4 to PHP 5.6 (the latest at the time). Facilitated cross-team collaboration among all major engineering teams and QA departments in order to achieve results.
- Initiated a program to automate the creation of base server images for our cloud servers. They allowed new servers to boot and begin serving traffic ~75% faster.
- Began investigating ways to implement configuration-as-code for our cloud infrastructure.

#### Senior API Engineer (April 2014—April 2015)

- Took the lead on the company's <u>HackerOne</u> program, coordinating across teams to address security issues.
- Built a development environment for engineering teams. Reduced new engineer onboarding time from 2 weeks → 1 day.
- Instrumental in designing WePay's MFA-as-a-Service offering. (U.S. patent filing <u>US15042104</u>)
- Developed new API endpoints to help expand WePay's business and support its partners.

### Amazon Web Services — Seattle, WA

### Web Development Engineer II (March 2010—April 2014)

- AWS hard-forked my open-source CloudFusion project into the AWS SDK for PHP, then hired me to work on it.
- Collaborated with the AWS Elastic Beanstalk team to provide PHP support for the platform, which launched in March 2012.
- Played a key role in the creation and development of the <u>AWS SDK for PHP</u> v2, incorporating significant changes in the PHP language and community since CloudFusion was first written in 2005.
- Collaborated with the AWS Design team on the <u>AWS Management Console</u>, to build a robust and user-friendly console. Led one of the first teams to provide reusable UI building blocks at AWS.

• Focusing on Amazon's *Customer Obsession* leadership principle, I successfully pushed for being better stewards of our community. Included increased transparency, better communication, and improved tooling for developers. [Examples]

# **Projects**

Proof that I can code, call APIs, interact with SDKs, and build user-facing software. I have live-coding anxiety, so live-coding interviews will always present me at my worst, not my best.

- **DevSec Tools:** Building a <u>website</u>, <u>CLI tool</u>, <u>and Go library</u> for helping developers identify potential web security configuration issues (in-progress).
- Custom Linux Packages: Building a repository of custom Linux packages (in-progress).
- CSP Evaluator: Building a parser and evaluator for Content Security Policy (CSP) directives in Go (in-progress).
- Terraform Provider: Built a custom provider which provides a set of utility functions for use in Terraform/OpenTofu.
- Multi-Platform Docker: Built a downloader for GitHub release assets which simplifies building multi-platform images.
- AWS Organization Security: Built a <u>library + CLI tool</u> which simplifies the AWS pattern for multi-account organizations which they call "hub and spoke."
- AWS Session Manager: The terminal is the right tool for shell sessions. Built a <u>TUI</u> for <u>simplifying connections to SSM-enabled EC2</u> instances using your Terminal.
- Configuration for tflint: Built a tool for generating up-to-date configurations for AWS/GCP/Azure for use with tflint.

### Recommendations

See a selective list of recommendations from co-workers and peers.

# **Groups and Accomplishments**

- U.S. patent filing, "System and Methods for User Authentication across Multiple Domains" (US15042104) (2016)
- U.S. patent filing, "Hive-based Peer-to-Peer Network" (US8103870B2) (2007)
- Voting representative for AWS, PHP Framework Interoperability Group (2012–2013)

## **Keywords and Skills**

- Languages: Bash, Go, PHP (modern), Python.
- Linuxes: Alpine Linux, Amazon Linux, CentOS, Ubuntu.
- Cloud/DevOps/SRE: TLS and cipher suites, ARM64, AWS Control Tower, AWS Elastic Beanstalk, AWS Identity Center, AWS Lambda,
   AWS RDS Aurora, AWS SDKs, AWS Secrets Manager, AWS Well-Architected, Amazon ACM, Amazon CloudFront, Amazon EC2, Amazon
   ECS, Amazon Route 53, Amazon S3, Ansible, Artifactory, CIS, CentOS, Docker, EC2 Image Builder, GCP, GitHub Actions, GitHub
   Enterprise, Nginx, Packer, Redis, Terraform, kubectl, automation, cloud configuration security, multi-platform development, operational reliability, performance, scalability.
- SDE/SWE/DevTools: API design, API versioning, CLI tools, <u>CircleCI</u>, <u>Docker</u>, <u>GitHub Actions</u>, <u>Git</u>, <u>GraphQL</u>, <u>JWT</u>, <u>NFS</u>, <u>REST</u>, <u>Redis</u>, <u>Subversion</u>, <u>Vagrant</u>, <u>WordPress</u>, <u>XSLT</u>, <u>ffmpeg</u>, <u>twelve-factor applications</u>, automation, building platforms, code generation, defensive cybersecurity, multi-platform development, performance, scalability, software library design, software testing, technical documentation.
- **PM/TPM:** Confluence, Jira, building platforms, coordination with downstream services, cross-collaboration (dozens of teams, hundreds of services), organization of complex projects, product development, product roadmap management, project documentation, project management, risk mitigation, stakeholder management, technical documentation, vendor management.

# **Education**

Obtained a Bachelor of Arts degree in Design and Visualization from Silicon Valley College (now Carrington College) in San Jose, CA.

Graduated in November 2003 with a 3.84 GPA.